welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we call hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
all right everyone we're about to begin
welcome to the stoah I am Peter
Lindbergh the Stewart of the stoah I run
the stoic group here in Toronto Canada
and since we cannot meet in person I
decided to launch the stoah and I'm
viewing this as not just a space to
discuss and practice stoicism there
surely be some of that but I'm viewing
it as a digital campfire to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge of this moment today we
have Jordan Hall who's going to provide
a situational assessment and I'll hand
it to Jordan in the moment but how today
is going to work Jordan will provide a
situational assessment I'll ask him a
few questions and when I'm asking him
questions just write down your question
in the chat box and I will call on you
just unmute yourself and then ask a
question of Jordan if you prefer that I
read your question on your behalf just
indicate that when you write it down
that being said I'll hand it over to
Jordan uh what's the situation my friend
unmute myself thank you did you yeah
haha mercy all right so let me see I
guess the first thing that comes to mind
is a very clear sense of the I guess the
recognition of the fact that the primary
situation is is building chaos that the
ability to even try to grasp the whole
of what's happening in any particular
perspective and narrowly focus it into a
set of linear words as uh sort of
obviously not the right possibility so
I'll sort of try to just give some
richness of the things that I'm saying
recognizing that my perspective has some
things going forward and a whole bunch
of things that aren't and just put it
out there but the hope is that this
notion that there is a way of us being
able to rediscover this campfire concept
and to rapidly rebuild a capacity to do
the thing that humans are natively and
dad to do which is to come together for
my
kind of shared perspective shared
consciousness it's what I would say is
is the thing at the very front end so
there's lots and lots of things that are
going on in kind of the day-to-day and
everybody's unique circumstances other
unique circumstances but the one thing
that I think is shared is this event is
the prototype of what in fact everybody
should be beginning to get better at
doing so TL DR that's the beginning the
end so a note from our sponsor I need to
make sure that brett weinstein is called
out as the person who first and foremost
urged me to be thinking about that kind
of thing the notion of the campfire as
being both the the beginning and the
archetype of what it means for people to
come together in a place of where
consciousness arises so hopefully we'll
be seeing more of him on this front so
as I look around I noticed that my own
personal life there's such a very wide
variety of different places where my
attention is pulled I spent this morning
talking to literally actual Special
Operations people who are embedding
themselves directly into the gaps in the
medical system in New York City so one
element of the situation assessment at
least for people in North America is
that the kind of the capital of the
American Empire happens to be the hot
spot and it is within days of having
what is known as medical system
overwhelm and maybe did today medical
system overwhelm in a big way meaning
will begin to start having overflow
individuals who need I see who can't get
access to ICU and that will continue to
proceed in some sort of exponential path
over the next few days and weeks so the
the situation on the ground in New York
is a is supposed to real thing that has
really human beings undergoing real
situations but also serves as an
enormous archetype
get back to that in a second actually
let me jump to Sweden I was just getting
off a call with Nora Bateson who by the
way her virtual version of the warm data
labs also serves as a deeply deeply
insightful prototype or model of this
kind of thing done well so Peter I'm
gonna connect you with her Orville s I
was actually writing the email before I
had to jump onto this those kinds of
things need to be cross fertilized
yesterday I was on a call with Benita
Roy and she has a group called the
radical of who's doing their own
variation on the theme and my
conversation with Norah she was pointing
out the way that Sweden is responding to
what's happening which is on its own
knife's edge and there's a shared
sensibility that we're going through
something that is in many ways best
grasped not at the at the physical level
but actually at the mythopoetic level at
the level of you know the way artists
relate to reality and that there's
something that's going on there's
something where there's a there's
something so like almost how would I say
it well I'll just say perfect about the
nature of how this crisis is unfolding
that is shaking out the particularity of
cultures and the way that the the dark
shadow aspects of the Swedish culture
for example cannot help but become rise
to the surface switching back to the US
of A it's sort of almost funny that the
sort of the robber baron archetype that
is so much woven into the fabric of the
American story now cannot help but you
know dress themselves up in shiny gold
outfit and sort of brazenly show the
degree to which they are endeavoring to
loot the Treasury you know they can't
even be clever about it they have to
come up and stand on stage and say yeah
we're gonna blow through four trillion
dollars in the next 48 hours and by the
way this problem is no problem it's
gonna be two weeks we'll be right back
to business it's you have to expect an
enormous Lee a significant amount of
stupidity on the part of the people
you're talking to and it tells me that
there's more going on that there's
something happening where vice somehow
is being forced
to magnify itself to its maximum
proportions so that we collectively
cannot but address it directly and
there's something about that that I
think is at the center of it that I
think my friend Zach Stein is actually
the process maybe just published an
article talking about it is the war in
heaven meaning that there's something
going on that again mythopoetic the
world we've been living in the system
we've been living in has been rotten for
quite some time and there's nothing
really about at this obligatory nor
talked about it like imagine a
gingerbread man that's made out of
something that's like he has removed
that funny stuff he could make in
physics class in like middle school
there was like sand or cornstarch with
water or you pushed on a really hard of
a solid but if you didn't its flowed
back into a goo so imagine you poured
something like that into a cookie cutter
gingerbread man and that's your identity
that's who we are we sort of formed
ourselves against the institutional
structure and the expectations of the
socio technical environment into which
we had been poured but there is no
reality beyond that it's obviously an
effective and inadequate and as that
structure is actually not forcibly being
removed the goo that we are is beginning
to use back out and we're finding
ourselves in the kind of the enemy and
the angst to the liminality and Wow hold
on that was actually never real but now
we're forced to realize it wasn't real
and it feels really weird and bad to
actually take responsibility for who we
are in the first place oh and by the way
even our notion allottee of the idea of
an individual was a projection invented
sometime in a relatively recent past
we're having to go deep and we figure
that entire concept layering on to that
just to throw that visual metaphor into
some hectic notions I said okay now take
my image right now is I'm actually
seeing all these sort of these wires and
coils there's being shoved into that
cookie cutter these are things like our
our collective and individual traumas
that have been forced to be held inside
individuals and inside our bodies and
our psyches that were never the right
container in the first place and now
what happens is when that cookie cutter
shape gets popped off Nolan does our
identity and self begin to lose out put
those wires pop out into space and all
kinds of ways and it surfaces things
that we were holding back and this
should have been held in a much more
common location so campfires like this
and she's in fact discovering some
amazing things that in her warmed
the campfires that she's organizing
people are having these bizarre
experiences where traumas that they
thought were their own traumas actually
whenever their own traumas and there's
actually deeply inappropriate for them
to be trying to hold it in themselves
although it is unconscious that that was
the case and actually as they enter into
this larger space the liminality
actually begins to move the trauma into
his right location and something
transformational happens so that's the
situational assessment we're in a
situation where there's an arbitrarily
large number of specific things that are
happening that are appropriate to the
perspectives and location of individuals
and cultures what's going on in South
Africa is a South African thing if
you're not watching that pay attention
it's real in South Africa is a place and
the way they're responding is the width
of South Africa is responding
we saw Singapore respond the way
Singapore responded trying to respond to
me trying to responded everybody's
responses obviously the hard-coded
nature of the character of who they are
and where they are and surfaces both the
virtue and the vice in its highest
bas-relief and the characteristics of
the crisis embedded in the phenomenon
the largest systemic dynamics that are
operating in it's just creating a huge
strobe blood effect so if you're paying
attention you can see a lot of stuff in
yourself and the people around you and
the larger environment what I expect to
see soon and I in fact am not
particularly pressuring because it's
already happening I see it already is
people beginning to glom together and
beginning to form cultures that respond
in different ways than the entrained
systems that are jerking them around
back and forth you know very practically
there are now gatherings of people who
are looking what's going on let's just
say in the United States because again
economics and finance tends to be
closely tied to us some of our most
obvious vices I'm saying no no we're not
going to put up with that that's not
going to happen
the powers that be may think that
they're in charge but
they may not be and we may soon discover
what it's like to actually have what is
it 100 and 350 million guns and 15
billion bullets that may happen we may
start seeing communities just sever
their ties and say you know what we're
just going to take care of ourselves
good luck to you and by the way in many
cases that's already happening but not
quite as how to say grotesquely governor
state governors are recognizing that the
federal is any movement started back in
the Great Depression and blew up through
the latter half of the 20th century is
now somewhat rapidly being forced back
down the governor of New Jersey today is
being presented with the model of what
New Jersey needs to do as New Jersey and
it is not symmetric with what's being
done at the federal level and if he
doesn't do it then that question will
almost certainly be pushed down to
mayors and counties and corporations and
churches and communities because people
are going to have to start making
choices on their own and the basis of
their own sense making in their own
capacities because well to be perfectly
honest we cannot yet rely on the forces
that we typically have been told to rely
on to do the right thing . and certainly
not the right thing for us
that's okay because at the end of the
day I think that's what we all well I'll
just not say we all certainly that's
what I think has been the case for a
long time that this structure this
architecture that was actually very
effective at doing certain things in the
middle of the 20th century probably
peaked in the late 70s has been engaging
an increasingly delusional and manic
effort to maintain its control and
relevance but it was obsolete a long
time ago and to the best extent possible
if we can use this crisis in this meta
crisis to forces to move from
complacency and addiction into something
like a new form of agency it would be a
very very good thing the problem of
course is if we do that in piecemeal and
it is not a way to find some coherence
in that movement and smaller groups
begin to pull against each other that
creates an enormous new form of crisis
and so there's a that's what I've got my
eyes on right now to be perfectly frank
there's a crisis that emerges when
people begin to decohere and begin to
start to find new ways of coherence and
whether that in those new ways are able
to hold together in anything they could
there's no reason why there couldn't be
amazing but it's not clear that they
will
active which would be focusing on now so
if you have a question for Jordan write
it down in the chat and I'll ask him a
question right now and then I'll read
out your questions or I'll call you on
you to ask it to Jordan
so to circle back to that campfire
analogy John came in yesterday I had a
session here he talked about how the
campfire sword like a proto religious
space and and I'm feeling sort of like a
churchly vibe in the stole on the last
like eight sessions I've done especially
with like when I'm using more of the we
space tech and the frame I'm trying to
hold over this whole project is sort of
I think Jim rut called it the proto B
it's like this space is designed to fail
in the game a sense and you mentioned
all these other people are like doing
similar type like things and projects
and so I guess what is your advice or
recommendation to the hold the frame in
the space in order to be maximally
collaborative during this these times
well I don't know how many people have
been watching the conversations that
John and I have been having but one of
the things that I think is coming out of
that I really appreciate is the rescuing
of the recovery the archaeological
resuscitation of concepts and terms and
you just mentioned Church Lee so I think
it's let's be clear when church is not
the building the churches the people it
always has been the people the people
coming together and in particular
commitment in a covenant right we have
words to describe these things just need
to be able to reconnect with the actual
meaning of the terms a relationship of
care are the sacred we have that to a
relationship a right relationship to the
sake which of course is the moment of
meaning the moment of import the moment
of the source of which guides effective
choices so to enter into a churchy
relationship as the common to rediscover
that to rebuild in ourselves the
capacity to be in that kind of
relationship which is exactly the kind
of architecture that is equal to the
moment that we find ourselves in and I'm
not sure that we actually need to use
any of the language this sort of Jim and
I have sort of hacked with poor tools
out of the conceptual environment it's
not named game B let's just do it and be
the people that are acting in that way
we don't need to be telling stories we
need to be enacting them living them
and now is a very good time for it Joe
asked this question of John last night
he wanted to ask it to you again so Joe
if you can put yourself off mutant ask
Jordan sure thanks for doing this Jordan
uh like Peter said I asked this question
to Johnny v yesterday on a campfire call
it was pretty highly resonant with what
you were saying at the beginning of the
talk so I'll just ask it I wrote in the
eyes of regular people the people who
are in the positions of strategic
leverage be that heads of industry of
government of Education what have you
they seem to be locked into some sort of
game a fundamentalism and have been you
know for many decades which is
essentially the whole blue church idea
does the game B crowd seeing the people
who are working on this project sort of
behind the scenes have a concrete plan
for simply nudging these people's
direction making or these people's
decision making and sort of transforming
from nudging to sort of transforming the
framework entirely because like from
what you've written
start at the individual upgrade your
sovereignty upgrade your your integrity
and sort of let it scale from there but
you know from plebeian like myself it's
like well what more can I do
so are you asking the question of how
can I get President Trump to change this
framework omastar ask them questions I
get Joe Rivera to be effective I think
you've made it pretty clear in your
talks and the things you wrote how to
make Joe are very effective but I don't
know I don't know how that scales up aha
all right in some sense the scales
sideways but let's let's pause for a bit
so there's there's two big moves that
are going on in terms of that question
as far as I can tell one thing is to
recognize that you can ever change
anybody's mind and every endeavor you do
so actually hardens it okay great now
what you can do is you can be of service
you can tell the truth and you can
interact with humility I'm here to help
if you were interested here's my
perspective and by the way I'm probably
as out of touch and blindsided and
bullshitting myself as anybody else and
it's just trying to be of service now
there's another thing this is this other
things really really big and it has to
do with something like what's the phrase
where attention goes energy flows one of
the phrases that came into my head last
night was the calculus of cowardice I
think this is a big illness that we
suffer from Erik Weinstein is I think
the guy who first brought this into my
mind here what's the coward do how is it
that we've actually found ourselves to
be led almost exclusively by people who
run by the calculus of cowardice what
the coward does is the coward watches
the carrot maintains optionality the
card waits and looks and invites the
heroes to step in and put their neck on
the line now if the hero's right the
coward steps in front of it presents the
coward itself as being the here and
tries to steal the virtue that should be
flowing to the hero if the hero is wrong
the coward heaps shame and scored on the
hero for his foolishness and tries to
steal the virtue that should have gone
to the hero it is were coming upon us to
simultaneously be heroes but also to
know where the virtue needs to go and to
know that the coward the calculus of
cowardice needs to be one of the things
that we are aware of in ourselves - what
did we arere allowing ourselves to fall
into that trap then to what degree are
we are allowing ourselves to be fooled
by that trial because if we can get away
from it we can simply allow those who
are making choices on the basis of their
best sense making and putting themselves
at risk to be the recipients of virtue
to be recipients of healthy good
attention then we begin to
systematically down-regulate what
essentially was the analogy and bad
behavior again a very simple choice the
governor of New Jersey right now has a
choice he has an opportunity he can
listen to good sense-making and make
choices that are in the best interest of
his people or he can choose the coward's
calculus if he chooses a great that's a
good news that means the new jurors will
be better off as a state than the states
around it if you choose this path B then
everybody else needs to be aware of that
and they need to be very careful to make
sure that they're not flooded into
believing alternative and then what
their eyes are actually telling them we
kind of know what's going on but we're
very easy to confuse and to deceive and
of course confusion deception has been
to a very high level so okay so that's
one piece and the reason I bring that up
is this thing I wrote on my Facebook
page about the difference between
peacetime and wartime one of the things
that we know happens is that during
wartime which is to say during times of
crisis where choices have real
consequences and when the implications
of those choices can be felt quickly and
in a very visceral salient fashion
there's an opportunity to select against
cowards and to reselect for heroes and
heroes and leadership can be at any
level and in any way and they're
happening all over the place right down
in those into those emergency rooms
where nurses are manufacturing hazmat
suits that have trash bags and go right
back into the into the frontlines so
that's one piece right collectively if
we simply begin to make that choice and
begin to orient in that way and select
against cowardice and select for heroism
then individuals who are sitting right
next to the levers of power can begin to
find ways in themselves to either step
into that not the person who can make
good choices for the commonweal can find
themselves in power to do so and also of
course the individuals who won't you may
find themselves shamed or best rode out
on a rail now how do then we the people
step into it whoops I'm going to close
the chat window because I realize it's
going to distract me that's this and I
don't mean that in the least bit
superficially how many people are in
this call right now about 30 or 40 maybe
50 37 look I have digital technology
telling me exactly the number don't have
a can of manual how many of these could
you do as an individual in a day how
many of those need to be done stochastic
across the entire human population to
have effectively everybody and plus two
from everybody else actually not that
many
if you can actually get really really
good at it and start figuring out how to
flow that in a period of two or three
weeks we will have in fact developed the
capacity to begin to move back into the
meshwork of human interrelationships in
these campfire constructs and will begin
to self-organize into tribes it can't
help but be otherwise that's what we are
we find ways of finding those people who
are most salient and resonant with most
our values and our sensibilities but we
can also do that in a way that has a
meshwork connection so we're not tribes
standing next to each other with inside
and outside but we're actually finding
nodes that are part of a larger holistic
wholeness the evolution of our
collective individuality into these
fractal layers of connectivity is the
movement that has been named game B
discovering how to do that in embodied
practice by just doing it and doing it
and doing it with velocity and can have
been an openness and learning rapidly is
the answer to the question there is no
better solution to it I don't know how
to do that with a formal model I can
give you hints and some heuristics Mac
can give you Theory all day long but
it's not going to help you've already
given it right now that's in it's in the
hands of everybody to start figuring it
out and to share that collective wisdom
and to get better as practitioners I
mean imagine if I told you a story about
what a jazz van looked like
until you start fucking playing music
you're not gonna really get it but once
you get it and start feeling what the
group feels like it suddenly becomes
quite obvious and that's where we are
all right so we have a lot of questions
coming in I think would be good to start
with Amy's because it's pretty practical
on the ground level so Amy if you could
unmute yourself
so hi Jordan hi
I had one yeah super straightforward
practical what region country city do
you think has shown the best response
thus far and why it's actually a super
super interesting question because it's
actually hard to know what best means
because it's actually hard to know
exactly what it is we're trying to do
now in terms of inhibiting the rollout
of the virus with the minimum impact on
the normalcy of life Singapore is the
easy answer Israel by the way is also
more or less than exactly the same
bucket in terms of the context of their
local environment in some sense they
showed that their culture has high
quality sense-making in high quality
choice making in response to something
of this kind best I can say
those are clearly better than their
neighbors and Korea did pretty good
singapore did really good
[Music]
an interesting question and to what
degree is uh you know is this really
maximally healing from the things that
his jewel needs to heal from different
question
I can I can say right now that it really
really looks like Sweden's gonna get a
real good dose of medicine and they're
maybe they're making choices going polar
opposite of what you might call best
practices from an intellectual
epidemiological level and that will
excise a lot of demons
I think Norah talked about it as and
you've got your and I'll use my own case
you've got your somewhat naive and yet
inevitably rebellious twenty year-old
daughter is about to get her heart
broken it's not a lot you can do about
it it's part of life so it's a powerful
question I think it's a very powerful
question I don't know that there's an
easy answer if I try to provide a
prescription from a point of view I
don't really know the interior of Italy
and I can say that there's a sort of
obvious case study that Iran and Italy
should have as a clusterfuck in terms of
handling the virus but maybe a
clusterfuck is exactly what they needed
that don't mean that in like some kind
of area fairy next a new-age notion that
everything's perfect and that are the
slightest I'm just saying that there's
always an opportunity to learn from what
in fact actually happened like the key
thing that this thing is doing is giving
us a fantastic opportunity to look at
the mirror and having a very hard time
bullshitting ourselves but honestly I
would say that the the the answer to
your question will only be found in
retrospect those people who most
effectively cut through the bullshit and
learned the most fully about who they
are and learned about their strengths
and weaknesses and upgraded their
capacity to actually actually respond to
the reality of the environment they're
living in that's it
maybe it's us okay
Ernesto would you like to meet yourself
and read your question my question was
related to the fact that if you are
predicting or respecting movement from
cities to to less more brutal areas and
if you expect that maybe individual
groups will be repossessing like 20
million homes that are now empty in the
USA the question is whether I predict
that yes
how funny is that so I cannot give you a
rational explanation for why that's the
case and by the way no particular
timeline so it may not happen the next
weeks or months but the my yeah
Department that I rely on most to make
good guesses about what's gonna happen
in the future says yes I do you expect
that to be the case and the evolution of
this thing over say the next couple of
years maybe five on the outside okay
Tyson Wagner you had a question about q1
on yes thank you
q and on has this in my personal
experience of what I see in my community
this kind of captivating almost
seductive sensational thing going on in
the way it captures people's attention
and I'm wondering like what can we learn
about good distributed collective
intelligence from q and on and then what
should we be most cautious of when
looking at that and learning from that
that's a really good question thank you
by the way a bold question because as
you know even I think using the letter Q
these days tend to get you thrown in
jail so let's see let's think about that
so first off let's recognize that I
think the answer to the first part is a
lot I think it's naive beyond
comprehension to not recognize it that
was a very powerful valuable experience
from which we could learn a lot so what
are the some of the things that showed
up if you think about it and I was
watching it very closely for a long time
so some of the things that showed up I
would say are like cardinal virtues a
deep stuff that frankly has been part of
code any culture this worth of shit for
a long time
phrases like where we go one we go all
notions like own your mistakes notion is
like take responsibility for actually
digging take personal responsibility for
perceiving reality think bigger don't be
trapped in existing ideological
frameworks of what isn't what is not be
aware the fact that disinformation and
disinformation is everywhere so don't
stick to any particular point of view
and assume that that isn't Thoreau
tative
hope community connected with each other
helping each other now this like you
know in some sense it isn't that
complicated just to take a look at at
the mythopoetic archetypes of what
virtue and heroism and wholesomeness
have always looked like and do that and
to the degree to which the Q community
found that and upregulated that that is
the strong positive virtues that are in
fact in that community alright let's go
to the opposite direction it's weird
because it seems to hold both
simultaneously which is kind of an
interesting thing well there's a certain
mania there's a certain manic psychotic
Sensibility a we live in a psychotic age
and we live in a psychotic age because
we all have the capacity to interact
with far more
information about reality then a our
minds can handle and far less
information about reality than be
actually tells us much about reality so
in an environment we can tell really
awesome stories we can weave together
narratives that sort of hold the
information that we've been able to
gather and hold into something like a
coherent story and then we try to
fact-check that by actually doing more
information this is what I think we're
the key phenomena has it's one of his
biggest gaps is that it's so bound to
the virtual and it's so capable I've
been researching things at the virtual
but then tries to draw conjectures on
the basis inference and hypothesis and
models of nature and and models about
what the underlying the axiomatic
structures of reality are so if you
think that I don't know let's go with
something
you think there's an organization called
Rizvi 2 verse which is tied to the Saudi
royal family and they have certain
capacities and agendas then you can use
that assumption complex about which you
have no in reality to explain a very
large number of phenomena now you're
gonna get a whole bunch of anomalous
phenomena around that but you're gonna
pretend to ignore the anomalous but now
I'm gonna be really happy about the
thing that's inside your explanatory
framework which is you say the key
phenomenon gives us bas-relief on the
weakness of the paradigmatic mind pull
stop it tend to be psychotic and manic
and to be self was the term biased
towards its own self referentiality
and of course we also seen a tendency a
strong tendency although not necessarily
a overwhelming tendency to engage in the
exact opposite of responsibility to
externalize to hope that someone else is
in charge and will in fact take care of
us and I believe that is also
unfortunate at the end of the day false
which is to say only this to the degree
which there are people who are in
positions of power authority
responsibility who have our best
interest in nine great awesome if we
take responsibility for ourselves with
complete integrity then their interest
in our interests would be completely
aligned so we don't need to worry about
whether they're there or not but to the
degree to which we alienate ourselves
from our own agency just sort of step
back and really hope they're doing a
good job and become cheerleaders or fans
in a sporting event and they're the team
on the field and we're the guys the
butts in the seats we've done exactly
the wrong thing
I'm sure there's more but that's that's
enough for now I reckon okay
Isaiah so you had a question about
initiation video games and masculinity
yeah sorry damn I got on the previous
situational assessment that you did you
mentioned something about how kids
playing Minecraft a lot of untapped
potential to deal with like the issues
in the meta crisis and I've recently
read a lot of them Jungian thinkers like
Robert Wise iron John comes to mind and
where they diagnosed the crisis of
masculinity is lacking initiation
rituals from boyhood to manhood so I'm
wondering if you have any suggestions on
how Gen X or little men can sort of
build that framework for the young
generation I guess another way of
putting it is how can you bring
teenagers into the campfire that's a
really good question that's a big deal
and I liked what you actually named it
in terms of Gen X Millennials and
teenagers right because it's something
about the phases of life that are
different
he'll do this
you're on mute 31 31 how many kids you
got I don't have kids right so you and I
are sort of somewhat the different
positions in terms of the this arc of
life and there's a couple of folks here
look like they're you know my senior and
pop a couple folks maybe your junior
then man oh man it sure is the case that
we dropped the ball on that isn't it
like to the degree to which we didn't
just not initiate people into adulthood
we sort of did exactly opposite in every
possible way so we've got a lot of
catching up to do and I got to really
say I have a bad feeling and I apologize
for that bad feeling but I have a bad
feeling that
my elders they're the ones who had an
opportunity to actually have what's
called intergenerational transmission
but for whatever reason chose to step
away from that and did not rebuild it in
a new way Delius to it to my awareness
so we're kind of happy to go inside we
can't rely on rituals or traditions that
been handed down to us because whenever
originals traditions were handed down to
us or other handed down and dropped and
left behind or so out of place that we
don't know how to use them while now we
can recover stuff from from older
environments and there's actually some
pretty good stuff out there that other
cultures still do and use but we should
be careful not to simulate and I use I
oftentimes refer to the folks who wear
way too many feathers I mean I think you
know who I'm talking about I'm gonna
call that a certain simulation but there
are lots of good things that exist in
lots of cultures around the world that
understand how to do this thing well
what I would say is that here's more or
less than nature the beasts each of us
has kind of cohorts the Boomers the Xers
the Millennials and Gen Z have sort of
like a generational crisis that has to
do with something like the the thing
that we have to get over to some extent
the boomers have to get over and I'm
just gonna call it narcissism and it has
to do with something like I mean can we
look for Frank when they were young they
were golden children right and
everything whether they is individuals I
think everybody's an individual their
life arc as individuals quite diverse
but as a generation things kind of
worked out they have an embodied sense
of things kind of working out but now
they're into life and by the way with
this virus that may be closed into life
and they maybe thought they were going
to be and it's the ability to turn their
attention towards what is in fact the
legacy of their generation to recognize
that they probably don't have a lot in
the terms of let's call it know-how
to say their expertise is expertise
associate with an environment that is
increasingly in the past but they have a
whole lot in terms of wisdom know so I'm
not really that interested in most cases
that in all cases in your institutional
knowledge I don't really care that much
about how the Federal Reserve works
because it's going to go away real quick
I care a whole lot about life I care a
whole lot about meaning I care a whole
lot about how what it was actually like
back in the day when communities really
existed and people really cared for each
other what is actually valuable where
she would be orienting our attention
what really matters fine elders elder I
need the elders to elder so then he got
my cohort he's poor fucking slackers of
Gen X we got to get over to ourselves
and stop being me lists we just have to
actually step in and say okay some of us
have actually built a capacity to have
some level of effectiveness in the
moment and most of us have skin in the
game and we actually have kids that we
care about so we have an embodied
relationship with our own bodies have
competence and expertise but our
biological bodies put us very much in
the this thing needs to happen but in
many ways we also don't really know what
to do we're behind the curve so we need
to support we need to put ourselves in a
support role to help the Millennials do
the things that folks know at the end of
the day the loads gonna fall on the
Millennials to make this thing happen
that just needs to be clear all right so
the Millennials responsibility and dr.
Jordan Peterson I think showed up as a
teleportation from this future for
better or for worse but he shook a whole
lot of people into recognizing that is
the millennial crisis balls in your
hands guys step up it's all there is to
it take about what happened in World War
two all right in World War two a whole
bunch of 20 and 25 year old kids got
thrown right in the middle of
machine-gun bullets they had to carry
the responsibility for the war in their
bodies and if they didn't the whole
thing was over right it was it wasn't
there the equivalent of Gen X and the
boom is Franklin Roosevelt was doing
fireside chats and Patton was sitting
back behind the back lines trying to
help people make good choices it was the
kids in the front lines who were
actually tearing most of the load that's
kind of where we are now but of course
our front lines are spiritual
lines and community frontlines and
relearning how to do those things from
scratch now in some sense you have the
enormous advantage that our educational
systems complete shit-shit which to say
they didn't trade you very well which
means you can just kind of throw it out
the back door and relearn really quickly
on the other hand the reality is that
the Millennials have an incredible level
of capacity like extraordinary level of
capacity both in terms of just sheer
smarts and also in terms of a cart the
ball we dropped in certain training
masculinity actually built up capacities
and young men that we would not have
otherwise had now my generation doesn't
have a lot of the capacities that your
generation has that are going to be
needful right now and things like
empathy and self-awareness and EQ just
talk to a like a real actual boomer man
and get a sense of how fragile the EQ
was of that particular generation so
take those capacities and then reboot
that with a new sensibility of what a
new masculine masculinity looks like and
recognize that just imagine that you're
you are going to be responsible for a
family what does that feel like what
does it mean to prepare a territory
where you actually take responsibility
for the area around you what does it
mean to actually identify in your body
the feeling of other men who can
actually stand arm and arm your shoulder
and shoulder and turn themselves towards
the threat and stand and have a break
against them right if you can feel that
energy that's the energy to get into now
we've got the other side we've been
talking a lot about men but this is of
course fundamentally of female crisis
let's be very clear
feminine energy is that which is being
called up in the hardest level across
all generations I don't even know what
that looks like I just know it's the
case I can feel it every time I feel it
in my wife for example as she digs
deeper and deeper and deeper into
learning how to discover in herself the
anchor grounding there's actually a
really good story it's the very first
chapter of The Grapes of Wrath anybody
read them
it's like it's exactly the situation
alright so it looks like this it's like
maybe even like the first three three
paragraphs he Steinbeck talks about the
here's the this the Okies the the the
sharecroppers and the men they go out
and they they put their hands in the
dirt they sifted they look at this at
the sky and they look at the crops and
they chat with each other and tried to
kind of figure out what's going on and
the women they're inside in the house
right they're holding the family and
they're holding the heart and holding
the the grounding and they're looking
and watching but then something happens
or suddenly you just get this moment
where suddenly the woman goes we're
leaving
she makes the call that this watering
hole is no longer valid your
responsibility is now shifted from
trying to make those crops work to
getting this family to somewhere
somewhere safe all right and of course
as soon as she says it you can see the
man just drops what he's doing in pivots
I don't know if you've been married but
by the way that's how it works
so that's kind of it and by the way just
learning how to do that at the simple
level is a really good practice and a
lot of people that happen to be forced
to learn that right now because we're no
longer able it'll really really distract
ourselves with work and school and
hopefully media and having to relearn
how to just be in relationship with the
people we happen to be stuck in
quarantine with but that's simple stuff
of right relationship between the
masculine and feminine the right
relationship between men and women which
aren't necessarily exactly the same
thing there's a big part of the nature
of this crisis the to the degree to
which we learn that and relearn that and
rebuild capacities by interacting with
other people and learning what works and
what doesn't work and deal with our own
fear and fear and limitations in
ourselves and grow through it as rapidly
as possible this also begins to talk
about what Joe was talking about I think
I've rambled on at length on that I
apologize
David you asked a couple questions
recent one about self deception and
shadows yeah so Jordan as we move from
theory to practice as we get on the
actual field we find out real quick
which of our notions are shadow
projections and which ones will grow
corn how do you personally address
embrace the courage to face yourself
deception honestly hmm well that's it
it's kind of an interesting question
isn't it because you can't really
bootstrap yourself into that because the
guy who's bootstrapping is the guy you
got to worry about so let me tell what I
noticed not just be very upfront we have
a my particular family situation has a
very odd circumstance which is that my
wife's pregnant
and we got some interesting data back on
that particular pregnancy and the data
makes things would say challenging to
deal with and so as I was doing like
taking my time out from dealing with all
the other crises that go on on the
outside and focusing time on what's
going on the inside
I noticed the desire to bullshit myself
I noticed the desire as I'm looking at
reading scientific papers to uproot the
ones that made me feel better and down
regulate the ones that made me feel
worse that's a pretty simple thing if
you built the capacity to just be
metacognitive to be aware of that
tendency to say okay well I actually can
tell I can kind of notice to myself
where my bullshit strategies you know
bullshitter is is strong but it's not
that sophisticated if you can kind of
get outside of it and allow yourself to
just be aware of the fact that that
bullshit just going to be working
overtime all the time and just kind of
have a mindfulness of oh oh
yep there it is it's showing-up there I
think that's pretty helpful you know I'm
saying and I don't think there's a
categorical answer because the second
you think you got a handle on something
that's exactly the place where you
create a blind spot so it's a little bit
like just recognize they just have to be
in it and try to be listening and and
how about think a lot of self
forgiveness and humility humility is a
key that humility really helps in the
bullshit front if you don't allow
yourself to become self righteous then
allow yourself to become right you
actually just really allow yourself to
kind of be in the middle of it and
looking and trying to do your best
that creates a smoother surface it's
harder for the bullshit to stick so
myself by the way I also resort back to
a lot of the tools and techniques that
I've been working on for the past five
or six years middle of these store of
practices or Buddhist practices or
Taoist practice and just take a timeout
ground yourself and go out into nature
I'd go at least two hours a day I try to
be as barefoot and these days since I'm
out and the Texas Dilek aren't you naked
in the in the you know in the flowers
the fields of flowers and just gonna
allow nature to flow and tune in out
everything and just listen to what's
going on and that creates space it
creates gaps it doesn't let the ego mind
and the limbic system to kind of narrow
your visibility when it fears the mind
killer
this is sort of like grounding as the
mind releaser stuff like that I think
those are good things and frankly this
is very powerful and I find that
then too much of my time focused on
trying to address things that you might
consider to be tactical and I can notice
upon reflection that I actually get very
locked into a sort of an optimizing
framework for moving sense-making into
action
how that feels because you have to use a
lot of sense making and you want to move
from a liminal space to an effective
space alright so how do you actually
move back and forth closing and open and
closing and opening and kind of
breathing and breathing out and using
nature and using people and using bodies
to be able to support you in that
movement and then I guess there's the
last one which is hopefully by this
point you know what your addictions are
don't do that be very careful mmm yeah
it's the circle back that Jordan
Peterson and he was my therapist for for
two years before he became famous and we
talked a lot about Millennials and
masculinity and during that time I
developed this kind of aggressive debate
debate modality that kept our bullshit
in check which you know Peterson helped
boost that signal so I might return that
to the the stoah could be helpful during
these these times knowing you had a
question sure this is actually
potentially more tactical so I hope you
do answer in a less tactical way that
may be appropriate so my sense is that
if you have this mesh type of structure
building not everything obviously when
you have individual responsibility and
grab bottom-up responsibility we you
know nobody can control anybody at a
certain distance and people may be
inclined towards many many different
interpretations and many different ways
of dealing with what's in front of them
and some of those may feel to them right
and good and it may not be and it may in
fact get pathological and they may be
taking shortcuts and the incentives may
be there to do things in ways that I
mean if they become us a force that's
that's destructive so how do you
communicate across different domains so
that we can that's people that can
influence things in a way that creates
more space creates more pause and
ultimately ultimately more of a game be
I guess answer we're more of a game B
outcome well
yeah it's funny cuz you said that to go
by can't I help but actually just go up
to sort of morning Direction principles
well here's my sense here's my sense of
it it's funny because I'm about to
reveal with my own personal addictions
but I found myself watching episode 2 of
the mandalorian yesterday I swear to God
I wouldn't be on Disney TV but we hacked
a free version so I feel okay about it
and there's that cool little
funny-looking character has that phrase
I have spoken and as you were talking I
just kinda had that guy pop up there's
something about integrity and I think is
the answer to the question again you
can't make anybody change their mind
okay I certainly can't make anybody
change their behavior you can to choose
exactly how you're gonna show up and you
can choose who you're going to be in
relationship with and what you're going
to give your attention they kind of like
that's it but I think it's a deep
insight that is often lost and that's
the human beings are obligate tribal as
individuals we are always always seeking
to find our tribe it's trying to find
the kin that connect with us with whom
we resonate and our place in there to
have no place actually it's fun actually
we're having a conversation with the
individuals is one of the last standing
indigenous groups in the North America
to have no place is one of the deepest
crises so in some sense feel in yourself
that agree to which the individuals
you're interacting with is this actually
your kin group is this right
relationship I don't mean necessarily
your genetic kin group I just mean
people for whom the relationship is the
right one and if not integrity integrity
do not bullshit yourself did not become
divided against yourself just tell the
truth
and I don't mean being mean I just mean
being honest with as much love and
peacefulness as you can muster to
communicate the truth clearly so at
least other people's hearts here and
even if their minds and egos dumb camed
supports right because absolute then it
becomes not just a relationship it
becomes an educational or a learning a
Paideia Kragh lationship because in
doing that yourself and learning it in
yourself you're creating something that
becomes a mechanism or a symbol or an
archetype or an avatar of emulation and
people are looking for things that show
them how they themselves can grow try to
be in yourself that thing which you hope
to be and then in so doing you will show
to others that to the degree to which
you are successful
they will show it to you and then you
can learn from each other it's something
like that it's just again very simple
stuff and listen to your instincts this
is we're now in the situation we're
thinking getting in your head gets in
the way it's okay to use rationality and
the deserve a keen sense and that's a
different kind of animal than trying to
use analytics or cognitive structures
you know hopefully by now you've built
some skillfulness and if you haven't
practice that and being able to have
good instincts make good effective
choices and just notice how to move
through mistakes and learn from mistakes
quickly look this is that Kairos moment
it's the moment of flow is the moment
where every choice has massive
implications it's not a Chronos moment
so it's time to be in it to unveil your
warrior self and dive into the fray you
have to dance and move and flow with
what is happening and what is real and
just be in it and grow with it as
quickly as you can
awesome so we'll end with one more
question two people had a question Nick
and Joel about the u.s. decision to go
put troops on the Canadian border
Nick would you like to read it out Nick
Kennedy hey Jordan
so yeah about 25 minutes ago the White
House said they are planning to put
troops on the u.s. Canadian border this
seems like a really novel piece of
geopolitical formation I was wondering
if you got any media treats ah ah well
unfortunately I've got now at seven more
or less equally weighted meta theories
about the nature what's going on
geopolitically and by equally weighted
what I mean is that I can't actually buy
us in the direction I did so what I have
to do is take that data run it in
through all three of these note that
they're probably all all wrong but at
least I get some to be a perspective on
it and it's not worth our time to go
through all the Madrid Italy what I
would say is and I say this more or less
everybody is aware the phrase don't let
a good crisis go to waste
the position to actually make effective
choices that are in the best interest of
everybody which means we've got all
kinds of little groups pulling in
different directions trying to maneuver
things and a lot of them are actually
trying to do bad things they're just
doing the best of what they've got but
it creates all kinds of weird
complications why we would put troops on
the Canadian border
let me actually make that a little bit
more clear why we would
why the fuck would we put troops on the
Canadian border that's the kids are
that's the appropriate question now it
says a good goddamn question I'd be
interested in anybody's perspective on
that who are these guys those troops
should be in New York City right now I'm
not in the Canadian border and I don't
mean putting down citizens I mean moving
things back and forth to where they need
to be yeah good question I think to a
foot shenanigans are going on everywhere
so don't let your conspiratorial 10:00
hat overheat but keep your eyes open I
mean there's things going on all over
the place and everybody it's a feeding
frenzy out there and the Russians are
moving the Chinese are moving all the
different sub tribes in the Western
anglo-american Alliance are moving
everybody is beginning to realize that
either they need to take care of
themselves the expense of everybody else
or they can start grabbing grass from
other somebody else's field so that's
another crisis is brewing by the way
just to be mindful the geopolitical
crisis is uh it's got a lot of tinder a
lot of dry tinder and I named this in
every situation of sense when I've
talked about it's been front front and
center and it's awfully front and center
right now so sadly I cannot give you any
clarity all I can say is yep that's
really an anomalous thing so we'll close
off soon
I'll make some announcements but any
closing thoughts Jordan do more of this
and do variations of it still is a good
one invite other people understood have
a bit in one jump into something like
the crazy hipster Burning Man thing that
I just did yesterday Bonita Roy to
happen to it Nora Bates is doing see if
you can yank Brett Weinstein out of his
chair and getting to engage in his
variation on this theme right we
probably need about 15 or 16 different
epistemological
a ladies driving this particular
construct and then had them Co
evolutionarily sapped each other's that
stuff will involved rapidly but groups
like this gathering on a continuing
paced basis and beginning to learn very
rapidly this is the answer to the
question very cool so as what Jordan
just said we have some interesting
people coming in Jim rut on Monday Robin
Hanson
Nancy Strickler from Kickstarter this
evening we have an existential dance
party at 7 p.m. and I'd love it for you
to be there Jordan to see your dance
moves and I'm sure everyone else would
like to see that as well I doubt it I've
been doing dances every night you can
bring her along as well so yeah check
out the website the store dossier for
updates sign up for the mailing list and
I'm viewing this digital Empire the
store as a gift for all of us to freely
use during this meta crisis if you're
inspired to provide a gift in return you
can go to the the gift economy section
at the bottom of the website for more
information
so thanks again Jordan for helping out
today giving us your feedback and
incense making and everyone else for
being on the call good thanks guys